Guide to the Roland Alston Family Papers, circa 1940s-1991, bulk 1990-1991 RL.11789
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roland Alston family papers
circa 1940s-1991, bulk dates 1990-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alston, William Roland, Sr., 1908-1994
Hogan, Judy, 1937-
RL.11789
1 Linear Feet Two document boxes, one half-size document box, and one audiocassette box.
The Roland Alston family was an African American family residing in Durham, NC. William Roland Alston, Sr., known as "Roland," became the head gardener for Mary Duke Biddle at Pinecrest then Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans at Les Terraces. This collection contains eight oral history interviews with Roland and ten photographs of his family.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Some materials in this collection are fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Roland Alston family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library as a gift from Margaret Rich in 2019. However, material transferred in 2023 came from a 1992 addition to the Semans family papers.
Arrangement
The Rolan Alston family papers are arranged into two series: Oral History Interviews and Photographs.
Biographical / Historical
The Roland Alston family was an African American family residing in Durham, NC. William Roland Alston, Sr. (1908-1994), known as "Roland," was born to Ena and Alice Alston in Chatham County, NC. He married Stella Elizabeth Atwater (1913-2009) in 1930 and the couple had two children: William Roland Alston, Jr. (1931-1995) and Joeseph Louis Alston (1936-2023). The elder Roland became the head gardener for Mary Duke Biddle at Pinecrest then Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans at Les Terraces, both properties located in Durham.
Related Materials
Mary Duke Biddle papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University. Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans family papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains eight oral history interviews that author Judy Hogan conducted with Roland Alston, Sr. and ten photographs of his family. These 1990 interviews are on eight audiocassettes, and there are five versions of the transcript from 1991. Three versions are annotated with corrections for a separate typist, and versions four and five are more narrative in format as a deliverable to a Dot (Dorothy) King. Topics include Alston's employment history with Mary Duke Biddle and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans; growing up on a farm in Chatham County; Durham and regional businesses, especially those for gardeners; his family life; and his views on relationships between people, including employers and employees, men and women, and parents and children. The photographs are mostly studio portraits of him and/or his wife and children.
African American families -- North Carolina; Chatham County (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; Durham (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; Gardeners -- North Carolina -- Durham; oral histories (literary works); Transcripts; Alston, William Roland, Sr., 1908-1994; Biddle, Mary Duke, 1887-1960; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent
- Oral History Interviews, 1990-1991
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Series includes fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  Scope and Contents
  Eight original audiocassettes with the oral history interviews and five different versions of the transcript. Three versions are annotated with corrections for a separate typist and versions four and five are more narrative in format.
  - Interview 1, 1990 October 30
    Recorded at 1044 West Forest Hills Boulevard (Pinecrest).
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0001)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
      Corrected.
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 2, 1990 November 6
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0002)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 3, 1990 November 13
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0003)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 4, 1990 November 20
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0004)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 5, 1990 November 27
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0005)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 6, 1990 December 4
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0006)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 7, 1990 December 11
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0007)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interview 8, 1990 December 18
    - Original audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL11789-CS-0008)
    - Transcript, version 1, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, version 2, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Transcript, version 3, 1991 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Interviews 1-8 transcript, version 4, 1991 (Box 2)
    Version 4 omits Hogan and is more narrative; corrected.
  - Interviews 1-8 transcript, version 5, 1991; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Version 5 omits Hogan and is more narrative.
- Photographs, circa 1940s-1980s
  10 photographs of the Roland Alston family, almost all studio portraits.
  - Roland Alston, Sr. studio portrait, circa 1940s-1950s; 8 x 10 in.; black and white (Box 2)
    Shacklette Studio, Durham.
  - Stella Alston studio portrait, circa 1940s-1950s; 8 x 10 in.; hand-colored (Box 2)
  - Roland Alston, Jr. graduation portrait, circa 1949; 5 x 7 in.; black and white (Box 2)
    High school.
  - Joseph Alston graduation portrait, circa 1954; 5 x 7 in.; black and white (Box 2)
  - Roland Alston, Jr. wedding photo, circa 1950s; 8 x 10 in.; black and white (Box 2)
    Cutting the cake.
  - Roland Alston, Jr. military portrait, circa 1970s; 4 x 5 in.; black and white (Box 2)
  - Roland Alston, Sr. family portrait with grandchildren, circa 1980s; 8 x 10 in.; color (Box 2)
    Includes some of Roland Senior's grandchildren and great-grandchildren.
  - Roland Alston, Sr. family portrait, circa 1980s; 8 x 10 in.; color (Box 2)
    Includes Stella, Joseph, and Roland Jr.
  - Joseph Alston family portrait, circa 1980s; 8 x 10 in.; color (Box 2)
    Possibly includes wife and two sons.
  - Roland Alston, Jr. family portrait, circa 1980s; 8 x 10 in.; color (Box 2)
    Possibly includes wife Rose Marie, daugher, and two grandchildren.